Guide to the Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts collection, 2012-2020 RL.11067
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2019; 2.5 Linear Feet 3 boxes; 102.5 Gigabytes 90 files
  - Creative Theses, 2019; 25 photographs; 102.5 Gigabytes 90 files 3 mov, 2 mp4, 6 mp3, 74 jpeg, 4 pdf, 1 docx files
    - Palma, Felicity, 2019
      From the artist's statement: "A reflection on memory, place and belonging, 'Fra la Medusa e l'Abisso' (Between Medusa and the Abyss) focuses on the interplay of an ancient Sicilian city, its surrounding land and seascape, and the many people who populate it now. Drawing from feminist critique of Freud's 'dark continent,' and playing with language and gesture, the film becomes a mythic antiland that examines the boundaries between historical and current, migrants and locals, us and them."
      - Digital film, Two digital files (.pdf and .mov formats), approximately 12.6 GB. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0017)
    - Rachkovsky, Tamar, 2019
      Digital documentary film submitted as an MFA 2019 thesis project. Includes artist's inventory and statement in .pdf format.
      From the artist's statement: "How do you know when you are home? Is it where you hang your hat? Or where you leave your heart? Moving from Jerusalem to Durham, North Carolina, I went from being at home to living as a foreigner. We were four strangers under the same roof, the landlady and her three tenants. With time and often dramatic upheavals in the house, with budding friendships, the four of us came to support and care for one another. 'Home in E Major' is a personal film, it documents a special meeting and a unique friendship."
      - Digital film, Two digital files (.pdf and .mov formats), approximately 44.3 GB. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0017)
    - Riazati, Sarah, 2019
      In this digital film shot in Durham, NC and other locations, scenes explore the legacies of slavery and war, class and race relations, and segregation in a Southern town. The filmmaker's written thesis, also in the collection, contains many reproductions of archival documents that form the historical context. Includes artist's inventory and statement in MSWord format.
      From the artist's statement: "... Through investigating the ripples of the words and deeds of local postbellum industrialist Julian Shakespeare Carr, paradoxically called 'the most generous white supremacist,' and reenacting scenes from the childhood of Pauli Murray, an unsung civil and women's rights activist, the film scratches away at surfaces of stories about Durham, North Carolina. Careful scrutiny of such surfaces may reveal effaced answers to the questions that history leaves us with today, regarding racial identity and segregation, industrialization and labor, and gentrification and community. In this time of flattened stories and controversial monuments in stone, 'monumental' will create a multi-dimensional, layered retelling of the life of a Southern city."
      - Digital film, 7 files (1 MP4, 6 MP3s), approximately 2.35 GB (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0017)
      - Scans of primary documents and artist's inventory, 75 digital files (.jpg and .docx formats), approximately 88.7 MB (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0017)
    - Smith, Dani, 2019
      Digital documentary film produced for the MFA 2019 which invokes in part scenes and landscapes from the American West. Includes artist's inventory and statement in .pdf format.
      From the artist's statement: "'West From Ruby To Rose' explores the personal, familial and historical memories transcribed onto the land. How does place change when new memories overwrite the old, and what happens when nothing changes, and memories and landscape continuously stay preserved as they were remembered?"
      "Parts of the films were inspired by Mark Twain's Roughing It, and the filmmaker finds that his prefatory in particular aligns with her personal narrative."
      - Digital film, Two digital files (.pdf and .mov formats), approximately 41.8 GB. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0017)
    - Waleh, Hannah, 2019
      Digital film documentary. Also includes artist's inventory and statement in .pdf format.
      From the artist's statement: "This explorative documentary provides viewers with a window into a unique family archive, in which photographs and home videos are juxtaposed with children's games. The documentary combines performances of traditional Persian children's games, along with animations and interviews to explore migration, gesture, nostalgia, adoption, international education and how the English language is used as a lingua franca today."
      - Digital film, Two digital files (.pdf and .MP4 formats), approximately 1.44 GB (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0017)
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2020; 5 Linear Feet 3 boxes; 1 oversize folder; 1 oversize box; 2 Megabytes 1 flash drive 1 digital video file in .mov format
  Magic lantern apparatus (Wei thesis) can only be used with supervision by a library staff member. There is a digital movie file showing the apparatus in motion, and explaining its operation.
  - Written theses, 2020
    This subseries contains the written theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2020 whose work is part of this archive. Submission of projects to the archive is voluntary. Theses are typescripts unless otherwise noted; titles are included when known.
    - Nguyen, Minh-Hoang, 2020 (Box 36)
      Typescript thesis accompanying the project "Lullaby for the 49th Day."
    - Styer, Alanna, 2020 (Box 36)
      Printed zine accompanying the photographic documentary project "A Prairie, Not A Promise." It includes transcripts from interviews, field notes, and additional project images.
    - Sun, Iliana, 2020 (Box 36)
      Final creative/written thesis in photobook format, titled "When We Say Vaquitas, What Are We Talking About." Includes one printed book illustrated with color doumentary photographs. Hard copy of artist's statement and inventory is included in the folder.
      From the artist's statement: " 'When We Say Vaquitas What Are We Talking About,' is an agile blend of conservation concerns and empathetic storytelling. Vaquitas are the world's most endangered marine mammal — and also the smallest. Native only to the northern Gulf of California, these porpoises are most often unintentionally killed by fishermen in pursuit of totoaba fish, whose bladders are illegally exported to Asia for their supposed medicinal value. This book brings the human characters in the vaquita's story together and examines four individual's varying relationships to the animal: a conservation biologist, a local fisherman, a Sea Shepherd crew member, and a student in a marine lab. A small animal can have great impact on a large circle of people. The battle around Vaquitas has been going on for decades and it is coming to an end. Witness this battle through the eyes of people that have different values and goals."
    - Wei, Mao, 2020 (Box 36)
      Printed thesis in the form of a zine, stapled, with some text in English and some in Chinese; accompanies creative project, "Manual City." Project includes photographic prints, a magic lantern apparatus, as well as a digital movie showing the magic lantern in motion and describing how to operate it.
  - Creative theses, 2020
    Subseries contains the creative theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2020. Hard copies of the artists' statements and inventories are included in the project folders, and an extract of the statement is available through the entries for each student in this collection guide.
    Access to the magic lantern apparatus in the Mao Wei project is restricted, unless used with supervision of ADA Curator or other library staff. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
    - Klos, Cassandra, 2020
      Portfolio consists of 26 archival pigment inkjet prints by Cassandra Klos, sized 8 1/2 x 11 inches. Hard copy of artist's statement and inventory included in folder.
      From the artist's statement: "This body of work examines the act of searching within this mythological Southern landscape. It is a visual narrative with nonlinear attributes, presenting no beginning and no end, but rather a series of moments that exemplify the curiosity of such an investigation of the natural world. In all experiences, there is an intentionality in turning their back on Southern preconceptions – finding their own mythologies and realities to depend upon, activating their communities with new ideas, and adding to the complicated and textured qualities of a Southern life."
      - Photographs (Box 34)
    - McPherson, Zaire, 2020
      Portfolio consists of 24 color inkjet prints measuring 11x17 inches. Hard copy of artist's statement and inventory is included in folder. From the artist's statement: " 'A Fall From Grace' is a multi-layered story told through the voices of now elderly women that were a part of a Charismatic Movement known as the 'Prayer Band.' This movement took place during the early 1970's through the early 2000's. It was comprised of single black women and children who followed in the footsteps of a self-governed spiritual leader...This series is a multimedia project that includes, photography, paintings, sculptures, and stained-glass pieces. This project is a complex layering of stories, that illustrates the lives of the remaining women who are willing to tell their stories and their long recovery back to their faith..."
      - Photographs (Box 35)
    - Nguyen, Minh-Hoang, 2020
      Photographic portfolio is entitled "Title Wanted" and comprises 25 archival inkjet prints: 15 reference prints (8 1/2 x 11 inches) and 10 large installation prints (22 1/4 x 33 1/4 inches) of the project as adapted to a home installation. Hard copy of artist's statement and inventory is included in Written Theses series folder.
      From the artist's statement: " 'Lullaby for the 49th Day' talks about and around the issue of memory regarding the Vietnam War. Using a combination of photography, installations, and live art, the project transforms the gallery into a space for mourning. The 49th Day is a reference to the last day of mourning in some Buddhist traditions when surviving relatives of the deceased officially wrap up the mourning ritual and resume their normal life. The project is a homage to the people who were not seen, especially the bombing victim of Haiphong City on April 16, 1972, many of whom died and buried anonymously. The photographic component of the project is titled 'Title Wanted.' The name is the testament to the impossibility of appropriately naming, and of remembering the experience of the War."
      Large prints are in oversized folders; please use handling prints in place of the oversized originals.
      - Photographs (handling prints) (Box 34)
      - Oversize photographs (installation prints) (Oversize-folder 3)
    - Styer, Alanna, 2020
      Photographic documentary project consists collection includes 14 inkjet prints, sized 12x18 inches (13) and 12x15 inches (1) from the ongoing project "A Prairie, Not a Promise." These fourteen images were exhibited at the Power Plant Gallery in Durham, N.C. in 2020. A zine featuring additional images from the project as well as transcripts from interviews and field notes. It is located in the Written Theses series. A hard copy of the artist's statement and inventory is included in the photographs folder.
      From the artist's statement: "Having grown up in St. Louis I was drawn to return to the Midwest region of the United States to document the remnants of the pastoral dream and industrial boom. As I traveled to county fairs and family gatherings, through prairie towns and industrial cities, I was reminded of the folktales and myths that shaped my earliest understandings of this part of the country; the legacy of native peoples, the passage of settlers in wagon trains, the echo of union songs and the labor of farmers. The chapter installed for my master's thesis explores how this history has marked and shaped the land and how land continues to permeate the culture."
      - Photographs (Box 35)
    - Wei, Mao, 2020; 3.0 Linear Feet 10 photographic prints; magic lantern apparatus in one oversize box; flash drive with one .mov file
      Magic Lantern apparatus may only be used in the Reading Room with supervision by ADA Curator or member of staff. A digital movie by the author is included and available in the Reading Room; it shows the projector in motion and explains its operation.
      Creative project entitled "Manual City" comprises 10 color inkjet prints sized 8 1/2 x 11 inches; a "magic lantern" apparatus with film transparencies; and a digital .mov video file showing the lantern in motion, with projected images, and explaining how to operate it. Written thesis is in the form of a zine, in the Written Theses series; hard copy of artist's statement and inventory is included in the thesis folder.
      From the artist's statement: "Inspired by 'Plato's Cave,' I create an array of self-designed magic lanterns that I combine with manipulated music kits. The spectator can use the handle to activate and play, at variable speeds, the worlds I have created. This project offers condensed, miniaturized, and fragmented images of the rapidlyevolving Chinese city landscape. An imaginary, isolated city is represented by landmarks and scenes from Chinese landscapes that jostle for space, including ghost cities, the Oriental Pearl TV Tower, factories from the northern hinterlands, a statue of Mao, and other metaphors."
      - Photographs (Box 34)
      - Magic lantern apparatus in box (Box 37)
        Magic lantern apparatus is restricted to use unless with supervision of ADA Curator or member of the Rubenstein Library staff. A digital movie in the collection, available in the Reading Room only, shows the magic lantern in motion, and explains how to operate it. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
      - Digital movie for "Manual City" project (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0017)
        1 .mov file contained in original flash drive